You get tough. You get tender. You get close to each
other. Maybe you even get close to the truth.
Chinatown is a crime, drama, mystery film directed by Roman Polanski.
Private eye Jake Gittes lives off of the murky moral climate of
sunbaked, pre-World War II Southern California.
Hired by a beautiful socialite to investigate her husband's extra-marital affair, Gittes is swept into a maelstrom of double
dealings and deadly deceits, uncovering a web of personal and political scandals that come crashing together.
J.J. 'Jake' Gittes, played by Jack Nicholson.
Evelyn Cross Mulwray, played by Faye Dunaway.
Noah Cross, played by John Huston.
Lieutenant Lou Escobar, played by Perry Lopez.
Russ Yelburton, played by John Hillerman.
Ida Sessions, played by Diane Ladd.
Chinatown is a 1974 American neo-noir mystery film directed by
Roman Polanski and written by Robert Towne.
It stars Jack Nicholson and Faye Dunaway, with supporting performances from John
Huston, John Hillerman, Perry Lopez, Burt Young, and Diane Ladd.
The film's narrative, set in 1930s Los Angeles, is loosely inspired by the California water wars—early
20th-century conflicts over water rights that enabled Los Angeles to access resources from the Owens Valley.
Produced by Robert Evans and distributed by Paramount Pictures, Chinatown was Polanski's final film made in the United
States and is considered a landmark of the film noir genre, blending mystery and psychological drama.
Released on June 20, 1974, Chinatown received widespread critical acclaim for its direction, screenplay,
cinematography, and performances—particularly those of Nicholson, Dunaway and Huston.
Chinatown led the 47th Academy Awards with 11 nominations, including Best Picture, Best Director (Polanski), Best
Actor (Nicholson), and Best Actress (Dunaway), with Towne winning for Best Original Screenplay.
At the 32nd Golden Globe Awards, the film received a leading 7 nominations, including Best Actress in a Motion Picture – Drama (Dunaway) and Best Supporting Actor –
Motion Picture (Huston), and won a leading 4 awards, including Best Motion Picture – Drama, Best Director and Best Actor – Motion Picture Drama (Nicholson).
It also received a leading 11 nominations at the 28th British Academy Film Awards, including BAFTA Award for Best Film, BAFTA Award for Best Actress in a Leading Role
and BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Supporting Role, and won a leading 3 awards – Best Direction (Polanski) and Best Actor in a Leading Role (Nicholson).
In 2008, the American Film Institute ranked it #2 on
its list of the top ten mystery films.
In 1991, it was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the Library of Congress for being
"culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant." It is widely regarded as one of the greatest films ever made.
A sequel, The Two Jakes, was released in 1990, with
Nicholson reprising his role and directing.
Towne returned as screenwriter, but the film received mixed reviews
and failed to replicate the success of its predecessor.
The film explores themes of dying and death, sea,
pedophilia, rape, mistake in person.
The tone is intense and mind_bending and dark.